<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-25T08:33:39+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DISI UniBo NLP</title><subtitle>The DISI Unibo Natural Language Understanding Group (DISI Unibo NLU), led by prof. Gianluca Moro, includes a large team of Ph.D. students and researchers which are part of the Department of Computer Science and Engineering (DISI) of the University of Bologna.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AAAI 2023</title><link href="/development/2023/02/07/aaai23/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AAAI 2023" /><published>2023-02-07T10:50:07+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-07T10:50:07+00:00</updated><id>/development/2023/02/07/aaai23</id><content type="html" xml:base="/development/2023/02/07/aaai23/">&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that our group has two paper accepted at AAAI 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Cogito Ergo Summ: Abstractive Summarization of Biomedical Papers via Semantic Parsing Graphs and Consistency Rewards” (Main Track)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Carburacy: Summarization Models Tuning and Comparison in Eco-Sustainable Regimes with a Novel Carbon-Aware Accuracy” (Artificial Intelligence for Social Impact track)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested check https://github.com/disi-unibo-nlp/cogito-ergo-summ and https://github.com/disi-unibo-nlp/carburacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We are proud to announce that our group has two paper accepted at AAAI 23.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://aaai-23.aaai.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/AAAI-23-Website-Banner_2560x593-min.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://aaai-23.aaai.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/AAAI-23-Website-Banner_2560x593-min.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">EMNLP 2022</title><link href="/development/2022/12/07/emnlp22/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EMNLP 2022" /><published>2022-12-07T23:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T23:25:00+00:00</updated><id>/development/2022/12/07/emnlp22</id><content type="html" xml:base="/development/2022/12/07/emnlp22/">&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that our group will be at EMNLP 2022 with an accepted long paper in the main track (22% acceptance rate).
We will attend in presence and present &lt;b&gt;BioReader&lt;/b&gt;, the first retrieval-enhanced transformer for biomedical literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;BioReader: a Retrieval-Enhanced Text-to-Text Transformer for Biomedical Literature&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;by G. Frisoni, M. Mizutani, G. Moro and L. Valgimigli&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The latest batch of research has equipped language models with the ability to attend over relevant and factual information from non-parametric external sources, drawing a complementary path to architectural scaling. Besides mastering language, exploiting and contextualizing the latent world knowledge is crucial in complex domains like biomedicine. However, most works in the field rely on general-purpose models supported by databases like Wikipedia and Books. We introduce BioReader, the first retrieval-enhanced text-to-text model for biomedical natural language processing. Our domain-specific T5-based solution augments the input prompt by fetching and assembling relevant scientific literature chunks from a neural database with ≈60 million tokens centered on PubMed. We fine-tune and evaluate BioReader on a broad array of downstream tasks, significantly outperforming several state-of-the-art methods despite using up to 3x fewer parameters. In tandem with extensive ablation studies, we show that domain knowledge can be easily altered or supplemented to make the model generate correct predictions bypassing the retraining step and thus addressing the literature overload issue.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://aclanthology.org/2022.emnlp-main.390/&quot;&gt;Check out the paper!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We are proud to announce that our group will be at EMNLP 2022 with an accepted long paper in the main track (22% acceptance rate). We will attend in presence and present BioReader, the first retrieval-enhanced transformer for biomedical literature.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.vinai.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/EMNLP.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.vinai.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/EMNLP.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">COLING 2022</title><link href="/development/2022/09/30/coling22/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COLING 2022" /><published>2022-09-30T23:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T23:25:00+00:00</updated><id>/development/2022/09/30/coling22</id><content type="html" xml:base="/development/2022/09/30/coling22/">&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that our group will be at COLING 2022 with two accepted long papers in the main track. We will present our works on &lt;b&gt;Event Extraction&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Graph Verbalization&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;Natural Language Generation Evaluation&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the list of the papers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Text-to-Text Extraction and Verbalization of Biomedical Event Graphs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NLG-Metricverse: An End-to-End Library for Evaluating Natural Language Generation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Text-to-Text Extraction and Verbalization of Biomedical Event Graphs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;by G. Frisoni, G. Moro and L. Balzani&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Biomedical events represent complex, graphical, and semantically rich interactions expressed in the scientific literature. Almost all contributions in the event realm orbit around semantic parsing, usually employing discriminative architectures and cumbersome multi-step pipelines limited to a small number of target interaction types. We present the first lightweight framework to solve both event extraction and event verbalization with a unified text-to-text approach, allowing us to fuse all the resources so far designed for different tasks. To this end, we present a new event graph linearization technique and release highly comprehensive event-text paired datasets, covering more than 150 event types from multiple biology subareas (English language). By streamlining parsing and generation to translations, we propose baseline transformer model results according to multiple biomedical text mining benchmarks and natural language generation metrics. Our extractive models achieve greater state-of-the-art performance than single-task competitors and show promising capabilities for the controlled generation of coherent natural language utterances from structured data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://aclanthology.org/2022.coling-1.238/&quot;&gt;Check out the paper!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;NLG-Metricverse: An End-to-End Library for Evaluating Natural Language Generation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;by G. Frisoni, A. Carbonaro, G. Moro, A. Zammarchi and M. Avagnano&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Driven by deep learning breakthroughs, natural language generation (NLG) models have been at the center of steady progress in the last few years, with a ubiquitous task influence. However, since our ability to generate human-indistinguishable artificial text lags behind our capacity to assess it, it is paramount to develop and apply even better automatic evaluation metrics. To facilitate researchers to judge the effectiveness of their models broadly, we introduce NLG-Metricverse—an end-to-end open-source library for NLG evaluation based on Python. Our framework provides a living collection of NLG metrics in a unified and easy-to-use environment, supplying tools to efficiently apply, analyze, compare, and visualize them. This includes (i) the extensive support to heterogeneous automatic metrics with n-arity management, (ii) the meta-evaluation upon individual performance, metric-metric and metric-human correlations, (iii) graphical interpretations for helping humans better gain score intuitions, (iv) formal categorization and convenient documentation to accelerate metrics understanding. NLG-Metricverse aims to increase the comparability and replicability of NLG research, hopefully stimulating new contributions in the area.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://aclanthology.org/2022.coling-1.306/&quot;&gt;Check out the paper!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We are proud to announce that our group will be at COLING 2022 with two accepted long papers in the main track. We will present our works on Event Extraction, Graph Verbalization, and Natural Language Generation Evaluation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://static1.s123-cdn-static-a.com/uploads/4165719/800_62fc19c314a5c.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://static1.s123-cdn-static-a.com/uploads/4165719/800_62fc19c314a5c.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AAAI 2022</title><link href="/development/2022/02/08/aaai22/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AAAI 2022" /><published>2022-02-08T10:50:07+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-08T10:50:07+00:00</updated><id>/development/2022/02/08/aaai22</id><content type="html" xml:base="/development/2022/02/08/aaai22/">&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that our group will be at AAAI 2022 with an accepted paper in the main track on &lt;b&gt;low-resource document summarization&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We are proud to announce that our group will be at AAAI 2022 with an accepted paper in the main track on low-resource document summarization.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://static1.s123-cdn-static-a.com/uploads/4165719/800_61a9409b89872.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://static1.s123-cdn-static-a.com/uploads/4165719/800_61a9409b89872.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>